<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Earle of Pembroke's speech in the House of Peeres upon debate of the citie's petition for a personall treaty, to be had with His Majesty in London. And also upon debate of those reasons given by their Lordships unto the Commons, for not sending the three propositions before a treaty.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E79aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E453_30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204953</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897358</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897358</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132713</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84497)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132713)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2496:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Earle of Pembroke's speech in the House of Peeres upon debate of the citie's petition for a personall treaty, to be had with His Majesty in London. And also upon debate of those reasons given by their Lordships unto the Commons, for not sending the three propositions before a treaty.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A satire, in fact not by Philip, Earl of Pembroke.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 20th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pembroke, Philip Herbert, --  Earl of, 1584-1650 --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Satire, English --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132713:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The <hi>EARLE</hi> of <hi>PEMBROKE'S SPEECH</hi> Jn the Houſe of <hi>PEERES,</hi> Upon debate of the <hi>Citie's</hi> Petition for a <hi>Perſonall Treaty,</hi> to be had with His MAJESTY in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo upon debate of thoſe Reaſons given by their Lordſhips unto the Commons, for not ſending the three Propoſitions before a <hi>TREATY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:132713:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132713:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>EARLE</hi> of <hi>PEMBROKE'S SPEECH</hi> Jn the Houſe of Peeres, upon debate of the <hi>Cities</hi> Petition for a <hi>Perſonall Treaty,</hi> to be had with His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>The CITIZENS being withdrawn, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſpake as followeth.</p>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thank God you had no reaſon to make me your <hi>Speaker:</hi> And truly (all things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) I have as little reaſon to be a <hi>Speaker</hi> as any man: And yet I will ſpeak; for I have been learning theſe <hi>ſeven yeares</hi> how to do it <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trumpere.</hi> I have help't too to baul down <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> and <hi>Scholars,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> for <hi>dumb-dogs,</hi> and doe you think I'll be a <hi>dumb-dog</hi> too? A <hi>halter</hi> I will: If I ſhould ſit ſtill and ſay nothing, and let His <hi>Majeſty</hi> come to <hi>London,</hi> that were the way to make me <hi>dumb</hi> indeed, for I can ſay no more for my ſelf then a <hi>dog.</hi> I hope the door is faſt, that the <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> do not hear me, becauſe I'll ſpeak my minde: What though I do not know my own minde? Yet I'll ſpeak it as well as I can. 'Tis known I am a true <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> though I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132713:3"/>cannot ſpeak good <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and as honeſt a man too as my Lord <hi>Say</hi> can make me; and therefore (my <hi>Lords</hi>) now I have lived long enough with you, I meane to dye with the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> or elſe (they ſay) I ſhall be no <hi>Lord;</hi> And ſo ſay I to you: <hi>Graſſe and hay,</hi> (my Lords) <hi>we are all mortall,</hi> and muſt be tyed up to the <hi>Manger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been for the <hi>City</hi> too in my time, when they would pay their money; hear reaſon, and invite us to <hi>dinners.</hi> Hang them <hi>Raſcals,</hi> they cannot ſay but we have given them their <hi>Belly-fulls</hi> too, (I pray God they do not hear me.) This time twelve-month they made a <hi>young man</hi> of me, and yet (as ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as you think me) I am an <hi>old man:</hi> They drew me into a <hi>new War,</hi> and made me waite upon a <hi>new Speaker,</hi> and <hi>Vote His Majeſties comming to London:</hi> But I was a mad man, I knew not what I did then; for, if the <hi>Army</hi> had not had the more mercy, I had been a <hi>Traitor</hi> as well as the reſt, for ought I know. Doe ye think then I'll Vote the <hi>King</hi> home again? no I warrant you, I am an <hi>old Bird,</hi> and ſcorne <hi>Chaffe,</hi> or to be made a <hi>Traitor</hi> any more for any <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> I am an <hi>old thing</hi> made <hi>new</hi> now: My man <hi>Michael</hi> tels me I am an <hi>Independent.</hi> I think I am a good <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> I; but <hi>Citizens</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> are <hi>Jewes:</hi> And who knowes but that <hi>Perſonall-Treaty</hi> may be a new name for <hi>Popery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may bring in <hi>Popery,</hi> and break the <hi>Covenant</hi> (if you pleaſe my <hi>Lords</hi>) but I dare not. I am ſure we have reaſon to regard it; For we have gotten well by it: we have gotten the <hi>Crown</hi>-Lands, <hi>Church</hi>-Lands, the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> Lands; every mans Lands too, if we pleaſe, and the <hi>Devill</hi> and all: And how ſhall we keep them, if we doe not keep the <hi>Covenant?</hi> For my part, I'll keep to my Oathes, and rather then part with them, <hi>Dam me</hi> I'll ſwear down all this <hi>Perſonall Treaty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And good reaſon too; for they ſay it will undoe all that we have been doing theſe ſeven years: And for my part, I thought all had been undone already, then what needs any
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:132713:3"/>more undoing by a <hi>Treaty?</hi> My <hi>Lords,</hi> if we muſt undoe, let us undoe as the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> does. They doe one thing to day, and undoe it to morrow. They Voted they would never make any more <hi>Addreſſes to the King,</hi> and made us <hi>Vote</hi> ſo too, and then they made us <hi>un-vote</hi> all again. And truly, I think this is a <hi>hard Chapter,</hi> for, I cannot reade the meaning of it, but I am ſure they doe not mean a <hi>Treaty,</hi> if they can help it.</p>
            <p>I like the way of ſending <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> I; for, I love to goe on <hi>errands.</hi> I am ſure it is an Honourable imployment for an <hi>old man</hi> to be the <hi>States half-penny-Boy;</hi> and I am glad, the <hi>Commons</hi> will not hear your <hi>Reaſons</hi> for the Kings comming, before He have ſigned the <hi>three Propoſitions.</hi> For, obſerve (my Lords) if they ſhould <hi>hear Reaſon,</hi> they might goe <hi>whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle:</hi> Miſtake me not, I mean if they ſhould hear any <hi>Reaſon</hi> but their own, and I think that is all the Reaſon in the world, for it is <hi>Reaſon of State,</hi> or the <hi>States own Reaſon.</hi> There I think I hit it; for, all other <hi>Reaſon</hi> is <hi>Malignant</hi> and <hi>High-Treaſon.</hi> Why then ſhould we Treat with the <hi>King?</hi> For he'll talk <hi>Malignant Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>reaſon of State</hi> too, but then, here's the matter (my <hi>Lords</hi>) he will not talk the <hi>States Reaſon,</hi> and therefore judge ye, whether the <hi>State</hi> have any reaſon to talk with Him, when He will talk nothing but <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and by that meanes (my <hi>Lords</hi>) make you, or me, or any of us all <hi>Traitors</hi> to our Faces. Truſt Him that will, for my part, I ſhall have as little to ſay to Him as any of you all, and yet you fee I am a good <hi>Speaker,</hi> according to the <hi>States Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thinke, we never had good world, ſince we had ſo much <hi>Reaſon:</hi> For my part (I'll ſpeak my minde plainly) I never had any reaſon of my own, nor will I own ever any but <hi>Michael Oldsworth's</hi> and the <hi>States,</hi> and <hi>by the life of Pharaoh,</hi> I think they two are as <hi>reaſonable Creatures</hi> as any in the world. But to this point of <hi>Reaſon</hi> I mean to ſpeak more, now I come to examine your Lordſhips <hi>Reaſons of State,</hi> which the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> have Voted contrary to the <hi>States Reaſon:</hi> For
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132713:4"/>as I take it (my Lords) they are the STATE, and you know we are all bound to ſubmit to the STATE, or elſe we are <hi>Traitors;</hi> I am ſure few of us but have been made ſo for not ſubmitting, and 'tis <hi>Gods mercy</hi> we are not all <hi>Traitors.</hi> Howſoever, I'll be one no more, if I can help it, but keep as well as I can to the <hi>States Reaſon,</hi> and I adviſe your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> to doe ſo too; for they care not a <hi>Fig</hi> for all your <hi>Reaſons,</hi> nor I neither. <hi>s'Death,</hi> I am ſure ſome of you have no reaſon to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; you know how you were whip't with the <hi>Black-Rod lately;</hi> and I can tell you, there's a <hi>black-Book</hi> too at the <hi>Head-Quarters:</hi> If you'll <hi>doe reaſon,</hi> ye may, but (mark ye, my <hi>Lords</hi>) <hi>it's</hi> very dangerous to <hi>talk Reaſon,</hi> it's the only way to be put in the <hi>black-Book,</hi> and then you know the <hi>black-Rod</hi> follows. I am an <hi>old man,</hi> I, and ſome of you are old enough too, but (you ſee) we are not <hi>paſt whipping,</hi> and yet you will not take warning.</p>
            <p>Howſoever, I ſhall have a care of one, and in the mean time ſee what reaſon you have to venture to talk <hi>Reaſon</hi> to the STATE. If you were their <hi>Fellow-Commoners,</hi> you might have ſome <hi>reaſon</hi> to make bold to give them <hi>Reaſons,</hi> but being as it is, me thinks you might know your diſtance. You ſay you would not have the three propoſitions offered to the King before the <hi>Treaty;</hi> Firſt, <hi>becauſe the Citizens here, and diverſe Counties have petitioned for it.</hi> The <hi>Citizens!</hi> 'Tis true, they have brought us in a <hi>Petition</hi> here for it. But the more <hi>Raſcals</hi> they: They may go home &amp; ſay their <hi>Prayers;</hi> for, they are not like to be heard here. What do they <hi>pray</hi> when they ſhould <hi>curſe? Dam me</hi> do they think the <hi>States</hi> a <hi>Camelion</hi> to live upon aire, good words, and <hi>Petitions,</hi> and <hi>Treaties?</hi> They were all for a <hi>new-war,</hi> and drew me in too this time <hi>Twelve moneths,</hi> &amp; now they are againſt a <hi>new-war.</hi> Is there any <hi>Reaſon</hi> in this, when the <hi>States</hi> have not yet done their buſineſſe? muſt They <hi>doe and undoe</hi> as wel as the STATE, and now by doing nothing quite undoe the <hi>STATE?</hi> They ſhal be <hi>hang'd</hi> firſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132713:4"/>
               <hi>Dam me</hi> they ſhal: I am ſomewhat the more eager againſt this, (my <hi>Lords</hi>) becauſe you ſay 'tis <hi>Reaſon;</hi> but yet I hope the Citizens do not hear me. I would not have all that I ſpeak, to be ſpoken on the <hi>Houſe-Tops,</hi> becauſe uſually (my Lords) I ſeldome ſpeak, but I am <hi>o'th Top of the Houſe</hi> before I am aware. But this I ſay, why ſhould they ſtand for <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Treaties,</hi> that firſt ſet afoot the <hi>war!</hi> And now when we expect they ſhould ſerve another <hi>Apprentiſhip</hi> to the STATE to maintain the <hi>war,</hi> they meant to leave <hi>Reformation</hi> like <hi>Dun in the mine,</hi> and are become ſo Popiſh as to <hi>Croſſe</hi> us with <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> If they were for a <hi>new-war</hi> this time <hi>Twelve-month,</hi> 'tis all the Reaſon in the world they ſhould be ſo now. What though the Caſe be not the ſame, nor the STATE the ſame now that it was then? I hope the Cauſe &amp; the <hi>State</hi> are alive ſtil, and wil be as long as the <hi>King</hi> and the Cavaliers live; &amp; out-live them too; for, They are <hi>the Same</hi> ſtil, and fitter for <hi>another world</hi> then the STATES <hi>world:</hi> For the STATES <hi>world runs round,</hi> and hath done ſo theſe ſeven years, but the <hi>King</hi> and the Cavaliers are the ſame ſtil: And therefore (my <hi>Lords</hi>) I ſhal conclude with as good <hi>Logick</hi> as any I have left in the <hi>Univerſity,</hi> as long as the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Cavoliers</hi> are the <hi>ſame,</hi> the <hi>CAUSE</hi> muſt needs be the <hi>ſame,</hi> though the STATE be not the <hi>ſame,</hi> but mangled, and rent, and patch't, and <hi>new-modeld,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant</hi> likewiſe crackt all to pieces. And where is your <hi>Reaſon</hi> now (my Lords?) doth it not follow then, that they ought not to take the ſame Courſe to maintain the <hi>war</hi> againſt the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> and not trouble the STATE thus with <hi>Treaties?</hi> eſpecially, ſeeing <hi>Guilds Hall</hi> is the ſame, the <hi>Exciſe,</hi> the <hi>City-Bags,</hi> and <hi>Publique Faith</hi> too, are all the very <hi>ſame</hi> ſtil, and as full and fluent as ever. And if theſe <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows</hi> that come here to vex the STATE thus with <hi>Petitions,</hi> will not go home in <hi>Peace,</hi> to forward a <hi>new-war,</hi> and be the <hi>ſame men</hi> again that they have been, I hope the <hi>Army</hi> will come &amp; pickle them up in the <hi>Tower,</hi> &amp; ſerve them the <hi>Same
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132713:5"/>Sauce,</hi> their <hi>fellows</hi> had this time <hi>Twelvemonth.</hi> For what other end (I pray you) do we keep the <hi>Army,</hi> or the <hi>Army</hi> keep us?</p>
            <p>And now (my <hi>Lords</hi>) that I have done with the <hi>Citizens,</hi> I ſhall fall upon the <hi>Counties.</hi> What have they to do with <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions?</hi> they are out of their <hi>Calling:</hi> they ſhould follow the <hi>Plough,</hi> and let the STATE alone to <hi>Harrow,</hi> and fetch in <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt.</hi> I warrant you they had rather have a <hi>King,</hi> and ſee us <hi>Quarter'd,</hi> then indure any more <hi>free-Quarter;</hi> but I think the <hi>States-Guard</hi> quarter'd them ſufficiently, and made <hi>drawn-Cats</hi> of 'em, I mean the <hi>Surrey-men,</hi> ſo that I think they, or the reſt, will have little ſtomack again to come <hi>a Petitioning.</hi> What reaſon then (my <hi>Lords</hi>) have you to regard what They ſay for a <hi>Treaty?</hi> They can but talk (you ſee) and the <hi>State</hi> can fight, and be nee'r the more <hi>Traitors</hi> for it; but if theſe fight, they are <hi>Traitors</hi> preſently, as ſoon as we have conquer'd them. I tell you (my Lords) if the STATE had voted me a <hi>Soldier,</hi> I would have no more mercy upon theſe <hi>Fellows</hi> than if they were <hi>Traitors</hi> in gingerbread. What though They would bite? I have ventur'd ere now the tender'ſt <hi>Member</hi> that I have, with a <hi>biting</hi> Thing, and <hi>layn in</hi> a month for it under the <hi>Surgeons</hi> hands; and I'll venture my <hi>Tongue</hi> with any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of them all, but I'll be ſure to have a care of my <hi>Head</hi> for the ſervice of the STATE; and who knows, whether I may keep it if there be a <hi>Treaty?</hi> But I wonder what good my head would do them: I am not weary of it yet, for, I never much troubled it, nor have been much troubled with it, and yet I ſhould be much troubled to part with it. 'Tis true, I for my part never got any thing by it, and I ſuppoſe no Body elſe will: Therefore they had as good let it alone. But neither you have any Reaſon to venture yours, nor I mine; and therefore to this part of your reaſon (my Lords) I ſay the <hi>Counties</hi> are as very <hi>Raſcals</hi> as the <hi>Citizens,</hi> that would have us to pull an <hi>old Houſe</hi> upon our Heads by a <hi>Perſonall Treaty.</hi> They would have a disbanding of the <hi>Army</hi> too,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132713:5"/>would they? Bus they ſhall ſnap ſhort; For, I love the <hi>Army,</hi> Dammee I do dearly. Sink me, they would have us <hi>disband</hi> I think too, and ſit no longer; but if the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> will love us, wee'll love the <hi>Army;</hi> for, why ſhould the <hi>Counties</hi> be ſo much againſt the Soldiers, poore wretches! Conſider (my Lords) an twere your owne caſe; for, it might have pleaſed God to have made ſome of us Soldiers. And ſo (my Lords) I think I have maul'd your firſt <hi>reaſon</hi> againſt the three <hi>Propoſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your ſecond Reaſon is, becauſe <hi>His Majeſty hath often declared, that he will ſigne nothing till all things be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and therefore that the ſending of thoſe three muſt needs cauſe delay to the Treaty.</hi> I would have you to know (my Lords) I am not for <hi>delayes,</hi> I hate them; for, I think I am as haſty as any man; but yet I care not, if we delay a <hi>Treaty</hi> with <hi>God</hi> or the <hi>King</hi> till <hi>Dooms-day,</hi> and that I think is a faire time; for, it may be to morrow for ought we know: And it is a very fit time, I think, ſince His <hi>Majeſty</hi> will agree to nothing till the concluſion of all things. I wiſh him well, he was my <hi>Maſter,</hi> but I care not much for ſeeing him, nor for <hi>kiſsing</hi> his hand; I can kiſſe my Lady <hi>May,</hi> and ſhe is my <hi>Miſtreſſe.</hi> I care not for kiſſing of men: I am an old man, and it is not for me to be <hi>kiſsing:</hi> but if ſhe be for a <hi>perſonall Treaty,</hi> then indeed this <hi>Reaſon</hi> holds good againſt <hi>delay,</hi> and I am of your opinion.</p>
            <p>Then you ſay too, <hi>it is contrary to the rules of treating to grant any thing before the Treaty.</hi> Have we done what we liſt all this while, and muſt we go by <hi>Rule</hi> now? Then it will follow too, that we muſt let the <hi>King</hi> rule again. He is in a fine condition to rule, is he not? I thought we could have ruled one another better than he. I am ſure my <hi>Lord SAY</hi> rules me, as well as ever I would deſire; and I believe he rules you as well as me;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132713:6"/>and then we can never be againſt the Rules of <hi>Treating,</hi> as long as he <hi>rules the Roſte,</hi> becauſe he ſayes a <hi>Treaty</hi> is out of all <hi>Rule,</hi> and none but <hi>unruly Fellowes</hi> do ſtand for it, and it is not for our Honours (my Lords) to be <hi>unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> But <hi>Dammee,</hi> I think we cannot be unruly; for, we have as good a diſciplin'd <hi>Army</hi> as any is in the world to <hi>rule</hi> us.</p>
            <p>But I ſay further, that it was the <hi>deſire of the</hi> Scots <hi>to have His Majeſty come to ſome of his houſes neare</hi> London, <hi>and therefore we ſhould yeeld to it preſently, to keep a faire correſpondence with them. Dammee and ſink me</hi> (my <hi>Lords</hi>) what have we to do with <hi>them</hi> now? we had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to uſe them a while ago, but now that they have helpt us to conquer the <hi>King,</hi> we have done with them. We (my <hi>Lords</hi>) muſt be ruled, but the <hi>Scots</hi> (you ſee) are the <hi>Lords of miſrule.</hi> For my part, I'll have nothing to do with them; I cannot abide a <hi>Scot;</hi> for, a <hi>Scot</hi> ſwitch't me once, and crackt my crowne with my owne <hi>ſtaffe,</hi> the very <hi>virge</hi> of my <hi>Lord-Chamberlainſhip,</hi> and now they are all coming to <hi>ſwitch</hi> you too. They ſay <hi>Hamilton</hi> is their <hi>Generall.</hi> He is a <hi>Duke;</hi> I cannot abide a <hi>Duke,</hi> becauſe I am not one my ſelf; but do not I look as like a <hi>Duke</hi> as <hi>Hamilton?</hi> Well, I might have been one, if I had had wit enough to keep that <hi>honor</hi> which I had: But I had <hi>honor;</hi> what then had I to do with <hi>wit?</hi> That's for <hi>Poore Rogues;</hi> for, <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>honor</hi> ſeldome meet together. I know many men count <hi>ſwearing</hi> to be wit; and if I had been ſo <hi>witty</hi> as to keep cloſe to my <hi>Oaths</hi> at <hi>Court,</hi> and not broke them by playing falſe with the <hi>King,</hi> and forſweare my ſelfe by taking the State's <hi>Oaths,</hi> and the <hi>Scots</hi> Oath: Dammee I had been as good a <hi>Duke</hi> before this time, as any <hi>Scot</hi> of them all. But hang <hi>Dukes,</hi> we are <hi>Princes</hi> now, an't pleaſe the <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>King's</hi> coming to one of <hi>his houſes,</hi> I know
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132713:6"/>not what that means, for he hath never a <hi>houſe:</hi> I ſay they are the <hi>State's</hi> houſes time out of mind, at leaſt theſe ſeven yeares, ever ſince His Majeſty was turn'd out of doores. I am afraid, if he ſhould come to any of his <hi>houſes,</hi> and we not agree with him, nor let him be <hi>King</hi> again, we ſhall be turn'd out of our Houſe, and the <hi>Commons</hi> out of their Houſe; and then we ſhall not have a houſe to hide our heads in. Mark ye too (my Lords) it muſt be to ſome one of his <hi>houſes</hi> neare London. How d'ye like that? I am ſure ſome of you have no <hi>houſes</hi> neare London, and ye thought to make bold with His <hi>Majeſties.</hi> S'death, I thought ye had <hi>hous'd</hi> him for that purpoſe, and will ye now give over <hi>houſe-keeping?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay likewiſe, there is more reaſon to offer a <hi>Treaty</hi> with him now, then there was heretofore at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Uxbridge.</hi> Well (my <hi>Lords</hi>) you may do what you will. <hi>Sink me</hi> if I don't <hi>live and die</hi> with the Houſe of <hi>Commons.</hi> I am for the <hi>State,</hi> I: But if you'll undo your ſelves with <hi>reaſon,</hi> I cann't help it: you ſee the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> have undone themſelves with it already. And if you'll beggar your ſelves with it too, and leave me to <hi>keep houſe</hi> here by my ſelf, you may. You know the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> and I are all one; and if you leave the Houſe of <hi>Peeres</hi> to me and two or three more, the <hi>Commons</hi> Houſe and ours will ſoone be <hi>all one</hi> too. Hang reaſon then, will you provoke the <hi>State,</hi> and leave my company for a little <hi>reaſon?</hi> You know whither my Lord of <hi>Holland</hi> is gone for his <hi>reaſon,</hi> &amp; what's become of my Lord <hi>Francis</hi> and the reſt, and where His <hi>Majeſty</hi> is with all his <hi>reaſon,</hi> and where I am that have <hi>reaſon.</hi> You talk of <hi>treating</hi> at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Uxbridge.</hi> 'Tis true, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> baffled us with <hi>reaſon:</hi> but how hath he proſpered after it? I believe it never did any body any good; and I am ſure, though we had <hi>no reaſon</hi> to get the better, yet we got the better with <hi>no reaſon:</hi> And therefore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132713:7"/>becauſe we thrived ſo well then without reaſon, I think 'tis wiſely done to deal out of all <hi>reaſon</hi> ever ſince. And ſo (my Lords) I think I have tickled you for all your <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> againſt our ſending of the three <hi>Propoſitions</hi> before a <hi>Treaty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now (my Lords) in the next place I'll prove the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions</hi> themſelves to be ſo reaſonable, that I know you'l never truſt to your own Reaſons againe. What though they are <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> yet they are not ſo, if I keep to my former <hi>diſtinction,</hi> that is, not according to <hi>Reaſon of State,</hi> but the <hi>States Reaſon;</hi> for ſeeing a <hi>Treaty</hi> would quite un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe the STATE, ſure 'tis all the reaſon in the world, they ſhould propound things out of <hi>reaſon,</hi> on purpoſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Treating.</hi> Therefore I'll mainteine the firſt <hi>Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is moſt reaſonable, that the King ſhould <hi>recall all Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations and Declarations againſt us;</hi> and well he 'ſcapes ſo too; for, I am ſure he ſlander'd us ſufficiently with a matter of truth, though he call'd us out of our Names: S'death! which of all us are <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traitors?</hi> Do I look like one? what, am I a <hi>Faux</hi> or a <hi>Catesby?</hi> I am ſure I had no hand in this laſt <hi>powder-plot;</hi> nor the firſt neither: I ſcorn to be a <hi>Traitor,</hi> I <hi>dammee;</hi> what <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations</hi> to cut off our <hi>Heads,</hi> and not recall them? you may chuſe whether you'll have 'em recalled or no, but ſink me I'll have 'em recall'd. What ſhall our heads be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with an <hi>Iron Cap-caſe,</hi> and ſet a ſunning theſe <hi>Dog-daies</hi> upon the top of the houſe here to ſpoile our <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions?</hi> dammee we muſt all come to't, if we be <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traitors:</hi> Traitor then in his face, if he will not recall his <hi>Proclamations;</hi> for, they will make us <hi>traytors</hi> in ſpight of our teeths, if we do not make them <hi>treaſon</hi> againſt the STATE. What though the Houſe of Commons have made us <hi>traytors</hi> in many things in ſpight of our teeths? I hope the STATE may doe any thing? and be no <hi>treaſon:</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:132713:7"/>Therefore I ſay theſe <hi>Proclamations</hi> are <hi>treaſon</hi> againſt the STATE, and ſo not to recall them is to be a <hi>traitor</hi> againſt the STATE.</p>
            <p>But the Cavaliers ſay, if the <hi>King</hi> recalls them, then he makes Himſelfe and Them to be the <hi>traytors.</hi> And all the reaſon in the world beleeve me, for, do what we can we cannot make them <hi>traytors;</hi> why then ſhould not hee make them ſo to our hands? for, I am ſure we uſe them like <hi>traytors;</hi> and one had better be <hi>traytors</hi> (I think) than us'd ſo: But they are ſtubborne fellowes, their ſhoulders are broad enough to beare any thing, and therefore the STATE hath reaſon to make them the <hi>Traytors</hi> I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber when they proclaim'd my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> a Traytor, and my Lord <hi>SAY</hi> here a <hi>traytor,</hi> all that ſtuck to them <hi>traytors.</hi> I am ſure I ſtuck to them cloſe, and yet I think we are never the worſe <hi>traytors</hi> for being proclaim'd. What's a Proclamation? I am ſure there are ſome in the STATE that have torn his Majeſties Proclamations. How can they be Traytors then? But I'll tell you (my Lords) who are the <hi>traytors.</hi> The Kings <hi>evill Councellors</hi> are the <hi>traytors;</hi> for, they never left him till we ſhut him up <hi>cloſe priſoner,</hi> and put them away. We are the Kings <hi>great Councell</hi> now: What though we will not let him come amongſt us? yet I am ſure we are his beſt <hi>Councell;</hi> for, we ſave him a great deale of trouble, and diſpatch all things for him without a hearing, and ſo I hope we ſhall diſpatch him too, if he will not recall. Judge you then (my Lords) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had not beſt recall his <hi>Proclamations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, for the ſecond <hi>Proportion</hi> for ſetling of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> there is all the Reaſon in the world for it: For, I ſay every <hi>tub</hi> ought to ſtand upon his <hi>own bottom:</hi> Why then ſhould not the Church of <hi>England</hi> be ſetled upon a <hi>Scotch</hi> bottom? Here's ſuch a deale of doe about a <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Religion;</hi> I tell you plainly (my Lords) I am an
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132713:8"/>
               <hi>Independent;</hi> I love it better than Presbytery, and yet I think they are both but a <hi>tale of a tub:</hi> But howſoever, it is an <hi>ill tub</hi> that hath no <hi>bottom:</hi> therefore (my Lords) I keep to my firſt ſaying, the <hi>Church</hi> will never be ſetled, till every <hi>tub</hi> ſtands upon its own <hi>bottom.</hi> Judge you then, whether I am not fit to be a <hi>Reformer:</hi> The Aſſembly ſayes, we muſt reform according to the <hi>Word of God.</hi> For my part, I never trouble my ſelfe to read a word of it, and yet you know I am an <hi>Aſſembly-man.</hi> What need I read the Word of God, when I keep a <hi>Chaplain</hi> to read it? Beſides, they ſay the reading of it would ſpoile my <hi>oaths,</hi> and I'll not leave one word of my <hi>oaths</hi> for all the word of God: But I am willing to be rid of the <hi>Scotch Oath,</hi> becauſe they ſay 'tis taken out of the Word of God, and it may be ſo for ought I know. But yet I would faine keep the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> becauſe it hath kept many of us theſe hard times, and becauſe it keeps the <hi>Biſhops</hi> away from us. I cannot abide <hi>Biſhops,</hi> they have ſo much learning and antiquity: I hate <hi>Surplices</hi> too, ever ſince Mr. <hi>Henderſon</hi> preacht it up for the <hi>Whore of Babylons</hi> ſmock. It ſeems he had taken it up of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, for he had many a <hi>Bout</hi> with her (as Mr. <hi>Sedgwick</hi> ſayes) <hi>now and anon too:</hi> But hang the <hi>whore of Babylon;</hi> ſhe is an an <hi>old whore,</hi> and I am an <hi>old man</hi> (I thank God) but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide <hi>old whores,</hi> nor you neither (my Lords) I hope. Therefore judge you, whether His <hi>Majeſty</hi> ought not to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Church-Government</hi> preſently, that all <hi>old whores</hi> may be excommunicated.</p>
            <p>As for our <hi>third Propoſition,</hi> for the ſetling of the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> I know not well what to ſay to it. This <hi>Militia</hi> is a hard word, and ſo is <hi>publike Faith,</hi> but yet the <hi>Citizens</hi> made a ſhift to ſwallow it. The <hi>Devill</hi>'s in their guts, they will downe with any thing theſe hard times; and they will down with <hi>Militia</hi> too if we would let them. Sure, it is a very <hi>hard word;</hi> for, we have much ado to make His
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132713:8"/>
               <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> part with it, and we are as loth to part with it as His <hi>Majeſty.</hi> But I think we have made him part with it in ſpight of his teeth. What though he will not give it us? we have it already, and we are <hi>fooles</hi> (I think) if we do not keep it. What, take away our <hi>Armes?</hi> does he think to make the STATE <hi>croſſe the cudgells,</hi> and be Popiſh again? The STATE ſhall order <hi>Hammond</hi> to trip up his heeles firſt, and if he cannot do it, <hi>Rolph</hi> ſhall go and make him <hi>kick up his heels.</hi> He is a member of the STATE's <hi>Militia;</hi> he may do it. <hi>Dammee</hi> he may, for, no body that I ſee dares queſtion him. Judge you then, whether His <hi>Majesty</hi> had not as good let us cut his <hi>throat</hi> with the <hi>Militia</hi> as without it. And ſo (my Lords) I think the three <hi>Propoſitions</hi> are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>reaſonable,</hi> and that you will never trouble the STATE with any more <hi>reaſons</hi> againſt them.</p>
            <p>Now (my Lords) for the <hi>Cities</hi> Petition here before us, I have but one word more to ſay. I ſay, their Petition is worſe than your <hi>reaſons.</hi> They would have a <hi>Treaty</hi> too, and no <hi>propoſitions;</hi> but they are not halfe ſo mannerly to the STATE as your Lordſhips; for, you give <hi>reaſons,</hi> but they bring not a word of <hi>reaſon</hi> that I can underſtand; and yet they will have no <hi>nay</hi> to a <hi>Treaty.</hi> Hang 'em <hi>Raſcalls;</hi> it is to ſave their <hi>purſes.</hi> They had rather ſave their <hi>purſes,</hi> than themſelves or the STATE: but Dammee their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and they are both <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>probates,</hi> and therefore I ſay the STATE muſt damn them both. It's poſſible in time the STATE may hang them for all their ſervices; I doe not meane the <hi>Aldermen</hi> in their own chaines; for, the <hi>Troopers</hi> will find other ware for execution: And well they deſerve it; for, the poore <hi>Army</hi> hath taken the paines to conquer the Kingdom, and them too; and yet the <hi>churles</hi> are ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, they never could finde in their hearts to give them ſo much as one meale of <hi>thankſgiving;</hi> therefore I think af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their cold <hi>breakfaſt</hi> before <hi>Colcheſler,</hi> they had beſt come
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132713:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>and fall aboard upon the <hi>City.</hi> I am ſure they have ſome <hi>friends</hi> here that will bid them welcome: <hi>Shippon</hi> hath a thouſand Horſe for the purpoſe; and I think they will help pretty well to fetch <hi>recruits</hi> out of theſe <hi>dogged fellowes</hi> of the <hi>City,</hi> and keep out a <hi>perſonall Treaty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then mark (my Lords) they'll have this <hi>Treaty</hi> to be in London. No other place will ſerve them to have the <hi>King</hi> in but London. I thought they had <hi>Kings</hi> enough at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don already: but they'll have King <hi>Charles;</hi> that's a <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant</hi> word if you put <hi>God</hi> to it; for, it is the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> word, and I am for neither. I hope (my Lords) you will be ſo too, and not turn <hi>Cavaliers</hi> now at laſt; for, what ſhould we do with King <hi>Charles?</hi> which of us can look him in the face? Dammee, I think you have as little reaſon to <hi>treat</hi> with him as I. Well (my Lords) I have ſpoken my mind; I pray you do not order the printing of my <hi>Speech;</hi> for, I would not have every body know my mind before my ſelfe. I ſhould ſpeak oftener if I might be leſſe in <hi>print;</hi> for, a <hi>Speech</hi> in print is neer kin to <hi>learning,</hi> and I hate <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> I hate <hi>King;</hi> I hate King <hi>Charles.</hi> Do you do ſo too, and le'ts love one another, and be obedient to the STATE: For, <hi>Dammee, ſink me and rammee nine miles into the bottom of a hedge,</hi> we are undone, if we do not make ſlaves of the <hi>City,</hi> and keep off a <hi>perſonal Treaty.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
